Finding Aid for Russell E. Bidlack Papers, ca. 1940s-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Russell E. Bidlack Papers circa 1940s-2003 1960s-1980s
Bidlack, Russell E. (Russell Eugene), 1920-
851282 Aa 2
Russell Bidlack was the first Dean of the School of Library Science at the University of Michigan, serving in that post from 1969 to 1984, as well as an author and historian. His papers reflect his interests in library science, local history, and genealogy.
6 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in periodic accessions by Professor Russell Bidlack (donor no. 2635 ). The most recent accession came from the Bidlack family in 2004. The Rumsey research files were received from Philip P. Johnson (donor no. 9977 ) in 2007.
The collection is open to research.
Russell Bidlack was born on May 25, 1920 near Manilla, Iowa. He obtained his bachelor degree in English from Simpson College in 1947. Subsequently, he received a master degree in history in 1950, and a doctorate in library science in 1954, both from the University of Michigan. He spent his entire academic career with the Department of Library Science at the University of Michigan, which elevated him to the rank of full professor in 1965. In 1967, Bidlack became acting chairman of the department. He then oversaw the transition as the department became a separate academic unit within the university. In 1969, Bidlack was appointed the first dean of the new School of Library Science. He retired from this position in 1984. His retirement years were busy with his research, lecturing and writings about Ann Arbor history and genealogy (notably his Sparks Quarterly newsletter). Dean Bidlack died September 18, 2003.
Bidlack wrote extensively on topics in the field of library science. He was also an expert on library accreditation, helping to write a set of standards, and serving for many years as the chair of the American Library Association's committee on accreditation.
The Bidlack papers consist of seven series: Correspondence, Personal Material, Class Notes, Miscellaneous Files, Writings, the John and Ann Allen Research files, and the Elisha and Mary Ann Rumsey Research Files.
Subjects:
Allen, Ann Isabella Barry.; Allen, John, 1796-1851.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--History.; Bidlack, Russell E. (Russell Eugene), 1920-; California--Gold discoveries.; Catholepistemiad (Detroit, Mich.); Children's libraries--Activity programs.; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.; Ladies Library Association of Ann Arbor.; Library schools--Faculty.; Library science.; Michigan--Bibliography.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Library Science.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Library.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Allen, Ann Isabella Barry.; Borup, Charles William Wulff, 1806-1859.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (0.4 linear feet) is comprised of two subseries: that relating to his tenure at the University of Michigan, and that relating to his work with the Sparks Quarterly.
  - University of Michigan
    - Appointment as Dean of School of Library Science (press releases, letters) 1969 (Box 1)
    - Retirement 1984 (Box 1)
      (selection of letters received; photocopies)
    - Search for Dean of School of Library Science 1968 (Box 1)
    - Search for Library Director 1978 (Box 1)
    - Papers relating to campaign to purchase brick at Michigan Stadium in the name of library science professor Ken Vance 1996 (Box 1)
  - Sparks Quarterly
    - Sparks Quarterly I 1960s-1970s (Box 1)
    - Sparks Quarterly II 1980s-1990s (Box 1)
    - Sparks Quarterly III 1991 (Box 1)
- Personal Material
  The Personal Material series consists of photographs from Bidlack's retirement party on April 6, 1984 and a brochure from his memorial in 2003.
  - Retirement Party photographs, April 6, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Memorial brochure and letter of 1945 (Box 1)
  - Ellen Raab reminiscence 1995 (Box 1)
- Class Notes
  The Class Notes series (0.5 linear feet) consist of handwritten notes on numerous library science subjects and used in lectures on such topics as cataloging, classification, and indexing. Some of these notes were probably created by Katherine Schwartz, a professor whose tenure preceded and briefly overlapped with Bidlack's.
  - Cataloging
    - Advanced Cataloging (L.S. 305) (Box 1)
    - Alphabetico-Classed Catalog (Box 1)
    - Audio-Visual (Box 1)
    - Bibliotheque Nationale Catalogue (Box 1)
    - British Museum Catalog (Box 1)
    - Brussels Catalog (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
    - Chinese Cataloging (Box 1)
    - Incunabula (Box 1)
    - Library of Congress (Box 1)
    - Linderfelt (Box 1)
    - Prussian Instructions (Box 1)
    - Reference Books (Box 1)
    - Theses (Box 1)
    - Union Catalogs (Box 1)
    - Vatican Rules (Box 1)
  - Classification
    - Cutter (Box 1)
    - Decimal Classification
      - General (Box 1)
      - Vassar (Box 1)
      - Walsh (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
    - Harvard Business Classification (Box 1)
    - Schwartz (Box 1)
  - Indexing
    - Editing (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
    - International Indexing (Box 1)
    - Library Science 140 (Box 1)
    - Procedure (Box 1)
  - Libraries
    - Ancient Libraries (Box 1)
    - National Central Library (Box 1)
  - Music
    - Cataloging (Box 1)
    - Dickinson Classification (Box 1)
    - Phonograph Records (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Personal Names, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Proofreading (Box 1)
    - Subject Headings (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous Files
  Of interest in the Miscellaneous Files series is a file of youth services brochures from major U.S. public libraries, ca. 1953. There is also a video from the bicentennial celebration of Ann Allen and material relating to the Willow Run Village dating from 1948-1958.
  - Ann Allen's Bicentennial, VHS videotape (Box 1)
  - Library School Class of 1948 (Box 1)
    (photograph with Bidlack's identifications)
  - Borup, Charles (Photograph) (Box 1)
  - Youth Services Brochures from Major U.S. Public Libraries circa 1953, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Bells at University of Michigan (Box 2)
  - Ann Arbor Quarry pictures painted by Milton Kemnitz (Box 2)
  - Willow Run Village material 1948-1958 (Box 2)
  - William McKinley Records, photocopies (Box 2)
  - Havens and Van Fossen Sons of the Revolution papers (Box 2)
  - Diary of Effie Maloney 1875-1878, transcription (Box 2)
  - High School Reunion 1993 (Box 2)
- Writings
  The Writings series (2 linear feet) contains many of Dean Bidlack's research notes on his wide-ranging interests. The series is divided into History - Miscellaneous, University of Michigan, Library Science and History, Ann Arbor History (unrelated to the Allen Family), and his research on the California Gold Rush of 1849 which resulted in the book "Letters Home: The Story of Ann Arbor's Forty-Niners" and Genealogy.
  - History, Miscellaneous
    - Ladd, Erastus (Box 2)
      (Article and Transcripts of Ladd's Letters from Kansas, 1854-1857)
    - Radio Scripts: "Prisoner of War Experiences" and "The Lighter Side of the Civil War," 1961 (Box 2)
    - Mrs. Gott's School (Box 2)
    - Henry Rice Mann, 2 folders (Box 2)
      (paper, research, letter transcripts photograph and negative)
    - Monroe, Michigan country history, 1 volumes (Box 2)
    - Rev. Michel Levadoux (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan
    - Report to ALA Nominating Committee 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Speech, retirement of Helen Stokes 1988 (Box 2)
    - Speech, memorial for Ken Vance 1994 (Box 2)
    - Letter on retirement of Margaret Taylor 1997 (Box 2)
    - Speech, retirement of David Hessler 1997 (Box 2)
    - Speech, memorial for Tony Kruzas 1999 (Box 2)
  - Library Science and History
    - Undated
      - "Early Michigan Libraries" (U of M, Detroit) (Box 2)
      - "Asa Gray, U of M's First Professor" (Box 2)
        (paper, notes, photocopies of letters, photos of paintings)
      - "City Library of Detroit, 1817-1837" (Box 2)
      - "Andrew Ten Brook: A Forgotten Figure in Ann Arbor History" (Box 2)
      - Transcripts of early articles relating to U of M (Box 2)
      - Michigan Library History (research material) (Box 2)
      - Karl Rau (research notes, correspondence) (Box 2)
      - History of U of M Library and School (Box 2)
        (notes for class lecture)
      - Notes for History of School of Library Science (Box 2)
      - History of the University of Michigan and Library (Box 2)
        (with notes and transcripts of newspaper articles)
      - History of U of M (Box 2)
        (notes and newspaper clippings)
      - Tappan period-U of M History (Box 2)
    - Dated
      - "Michigan History Bibliography" 1948 (Box 2)
      - Seminar paper, "The Board of Regents of the U of M, 1837-1852" 1949 (Box 2)
      - "The Coming Catalogue or Melvil Dewey's Flying Machine" 1957 (Box 2)
      - Speech for the Centennial of the Ladies Library Association of Ann Arbor 1966 (Box 2)
      - "Beginnings of Library School" (notes for convocation, January 15, 1976) and "The Book Collection of the Old University of Michigan". 1958 (Box 2)
      - "U of M School of Library Science History, 50th Anniversary" 1976 (Box 2)
      - "1983 Budget Impact on HEA II-B :Library Training" 1982 (Box 2)
      - "Library Education during the Holley Years at North Carolina, 1972-1985" 1985 (Box 2)
      - "Library Education at Michigan" 1987 (Box 2)
      - "Library Education at Michigan" (notes) 1987 (Box 2)
  - Ann Arbor History
    - "The Short and Troubled Lives of Elisha and Mary Ann Rumsey" (Box 3)
    - Speeches-"Ann Arbor of William Clements' Boyhood" (Box 3)
    - "Dr. Alvan Chase's Ann Arbor, 1858" (draft and notes), 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence re: Ann Arbor Street Exhibit Program 1996 (Box 3)
    - Ann Arbor History research and notes, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Washtenaw county research, notes and transcriptions (Box 3)
  - "Letters Home: The Story of Ann Arbor's Forty-Niners"
    - "To California on the Sarah Sands: Two letters written in 1850 by L.R. Slawson" (correspondence and notes), 1965 (Box 3)
    - 1849 California Gold Rush Lecture Notes, September 20, 1998 (Box 3)
    - 1849'ers Letter Transcriptions (Box 3)
    - Lecture Notes-49ers (Box 3)
    - Correspondence re: "Letters Home" (Box 3)
    - 49ers Research and Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Dr. Ormsby lecture notes April 15, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Dr. Ormsby Letters (transcriptions) (Box 3)
    - 49ers research and transcriptions (Box 3)
    - 49ers articles, photocopies (Box 3)
    - 49ers Research (Box 3)
  - Genealogy
    - "Genealogy and Folklore" (Box 3)
    - "First Steps in Climbing the Family Tree" (1958), Sparks Quarterly September 1960, June 1961 (Box 3)
    - Notes on Genealogy Talk, "Genealogical Research: Yesterday, Today, and Tomorrow" (Box 3)
    - Speech on Genealogy, Mt. Clemens Public Library September 16, 1983 (Box 3)
- John and Ann Allen Research files
  The John and Ann Allen Research files (2 linear feet) contains research notes, transcriptions and photocopies of original documents, and correspondence with individuals and repositories. The papers divide into five subseries: Ann Allen, Allen Family, Michigan History, Related Families and Correspondence (Alphabetical by name of family or correspondent), and Augusta County, Virginia research. Drafts and notes for his books "Ann Arbor's First Lady: Event in the Life of Ann I. Allen" and "John Allen and the Founding of Ann Arbor" are also included.
  - Ann Allen
    - "Ann Arbor's First Lady: Events in the Life of Ann I. Allen" 1996 (Box 4)
      in binder
    - "Ann Arbor's First Lady" (following publication) (Box 4)
    - Ann Allen's obituary Ann Arbor Register, May 9, 1877 (Box 4)
    - Will and estate of Ann Allen (Box 4)
    - Ann Allen Letters (Box 4)
    - Ann Allen's Bible (Box 4)
    - Ann Allen-Biography items (Box 4)
    - Carson Gibb correspondence (Ann Allen research, Maryland) (Box 4)
    - James McCue's account as guardian of Ann's sons (Box 4)
    - Phoebe McCue Bell's account of Ann Allen (Box 4)
    - Virginia Bell Somerville-correspondence (Ann Allen) (Box 4)
    - Notes for Ann Allen lecture (Box 4)
    - Ann Allen notes for lecture (detailed) (Box 4)
    - REB's Notes-Ann Allen lecture (Box 4)
    - Ann Allen manuscript-notes (McKim) (Box 4)
    - Biography of Ann (Barry) McCue Allen (Box 4)
      (draft copy by REB)
    - Florence Hazzard article on Ann Allen (Box 4)
  - Allen Family
    - Photographs-Allen and McCue (Box 4)
    - John Allen-Business References (Box 4)
    - John Allen-letters to and from (Box 4)
    - Allen-California Letters-REB paper (Box 4)
    - REB's correspondence Re: Allen (Box 4)
    - Allen-Postmaster AA 1824-1829, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Bentley Library Notes (Box 4)
    - Allen Family records (Box 4)
    - Allen-Misc. (Box 4)
    - Misc. Records-Allen and Rumsey (Box 4)
    - Misses Clark's School (engraving, Allen home) (Box 4)
    - Allen letters-Elizabeth, Sarah, etc., 2 folders (Box 4)
    - "Frame Farm"-purchase by Col. James Allen (Box 4)
    - James C. Allen letters, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - James T. Allen-letter to wife 1836 (Box 4)
    - James Turner Allen (Box 4)
    - Allen-Lamont Corn (Box 4)
    - Lois Allen correspondence (Box 4)
    - REB first paper on Allen (includes footnotes) (Box 4)
    - 1962 John Allen Booklet, 1996 revisions (Box 4)
    - REB's Booklet on Allen-First Draft (Box 4)
    - John Allen-biography for Michigan Historical Collection (Box 5)
    - Allen, REB's speeches on (Box 5)
    - Lecture on John Allen-notes (Box 5)
    - REB's notes-John Allen (lecture) (Box 5)
  - Ann Arbor History and related
    - Allen School-REB's remarks (Box 5)
    - Ann Arbor Academy and Manual Labor School (Box 5)
    - Ann Arbor History-Beginnings and Early History (Box 5)
    - Ann Arbor Twp., taxes and property 1830 (Box 5)
    - Naming of Ann Arbor (Box 5)
    - Corselius, Cornelia-Ann Arbor homes 1909 (Box 5)
    - Ann Arbor Chronology (Box 5)
    - Ann Arbor History Items (Box 5)
    - AA Newspaper Items (Box 5)
    - Masonry and Anti-masons (Box 5)
    - Territorial papers-Michigan (Box 5)
  - Related Families and Correspondence
    (alphabetical by name of family or correspondent)
    - Anderson, Catherine letters (Box 5)
    - Miss Anderson and Mrs. Heppen Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Barry Family records (Box 5)
    - Barry Thrift Brown correspondence (Box 5)
    - Bible-Barry (writings by REB) (Box 5)
    - Andrew Barry (including estate) (Box 5)
    - Thomas Barry, MD deeds (Box 5)
    - Will of Thomas Barry and estate (Box 5)
    - Bernhard, Karl-Travels-1825-1826 (Box 5)
    - John Broome letter (Box 5)
    - Caroline Campbell letters (Box 5)
    - C. Clark letter July 9, 1841 (written in Ann Arbor) (Box 5)
    - Mary Clark's writings (Box 5)
    - Crawford Family (Box 5)
    - Goodrich, Morell (Box 5)
    - Greenleaf Family, John Allen connection claim (Box 5)
    - Winchester-Rev. Wm. Hill (Box 5)
    - Hoefer Research (Box 5)
    - Justice letters (Box 5)
    - Kerr correspondence (Box 5)
    - McCue Family (Box 5)
    - John C. McCue Estate (not son of Ann) (Box 5)
    - Marshall McCue 1888 letters (Box 5)
    - Sarah McCue correspondence (Box 5)
    - Thomas McCue letters (Box 5)
    - Thomas W. McCue estate (Box 5)
    - Dr. Wm. McCue estate (Box 5)
    - McKim Family (Box 5)
    - Maynard letters (Box 5)
    - Dr. Benjamin H. Packard (Box 5)
    - Richmond Enterprise (Bollwood, Sweeter and Lyle Chapman's letters) (Box 5)
    - Schoer correspondence (Box 5)
    - James Sherer and Ed. McCue letters (Box 5)
    - Smith Family records (Box 5)
    - Smith, Sam-correspondence (Box 5)
    - William Smith estate (Ann Allen's grandfather) (Box 5)
    - Stanton-Civil War (Box 5)
    - Sullivan correspondence (Box 5)
    - Tate Family (Box 5)
    - Telfair Materials (Box 5)
    - Trimble Family (Box 5)
    - Waddell Family (Sarah) (Box 5)
    - Western Emigrant-Notes (Box 5)
  - Augusta Co., Virginia research
    - Augusta Co.-Maps (Box 5)
    - Augusta Co., VA (Box 5)
    - Augusta Co., VA Annals 1888, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Augusta Co. Bushman Research (Box 5)
    - Augusta Co. Census Records (Box 5)
    - REB's Notes 1978 Augusta Co. visit (Box 5)
    - James and John Allen deeds-Augusta Co. (Box 5)
    - Rockbridge Co. Deeds and Census Records (Box 5)
    - VA travel accounts (Box 5)
    - Virginia Deeds photocopies (Box 5)
- Elisha and Mary Ann Rumsey research files
  The Elisha and Mary Ann Rumsey Research Files (1 linear ft.) includes correspondence with Rumsey family members and research institutions, notes, typescripts of various documents compiled by Russell Bidlack in the course of his research for the booklet “The Short and Troubled Lives of Elisha and Mary Ann Rumsey.”
  - Correspondence with Rumsey family members and research institutions, notes, typescripts of various documents compiled by Russell Bidlack in the course of his research for the booklet “The Short and Troubled Lives of Elisha and Mary Ann Rumsey.” (Box 6)